Finding aid for the Sylvia Plath collection MRBC.MS.00045
Mortimer Rare Book Collection
- Personal papers, approximately 1932-1963; 3; .5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  - Financial materials: Checkbook stubs, 1960 January-1963 January; 14 items (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Checkbook stubs in an envelope from LLoyd's Bank. There is a list of poems in Plath's hand on the back, in two columns headed "Harper's" and "Observer".
  - Financial materials: Receipt from The Kenyon Review, 1960 August 28 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Receipt for payment of $25.00 for "verse in The Kenyon Review, Autumn 1960." The poems "The Colossus" and "The Beekeeper's Daughter" appeared in this issue.
  - Financial materials: Copyright assignment, 1961 October-November; 4 pages (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Typed legal document (one page is a photostat) in which The New Yorker Magazine, Inc., transfers to Sylvia Plath the "right, title and interest" in the copyrights to four of her poems, which appeared in The New Yorker from August 1958 - May 1960.
  - Financial materials: Miscellaneous calculations, 1961-1962; 1 pages (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Handwritten calculations in Plath's hand on the back of an envelope from LLoyd's Bank (postmarked 1961 June 14). According to Ted Hughes, calculations pertain to the purchase of Court Green, their home in Devon. The calculations show checkbook deposits and checks written (#794-816). "June 1" is written on the bottom of the right hand column. Ted Hughes has recorded two other expenses on the front of the envelope, dated 1961 Nov 4 and 1962 Mar 23.
  - Memorabilia: Birth announcement, 1932 October 27; Printed card with pink trim and ribbon. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Birth announcement for Sylvia Plath with "Sylvia Plath 8 3/4 lbs.," parents' names, and date written on the card, along with the message "Mother and baby are fine!"
    Gift of Aurelia S. Plath. 12/03/1983.
  - Memorabilia: Postcard from Quiz Kids (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Postcard from the Quiz Kids program thanking Sylvia Plath for the question she submitted.
  - Memorabilia: Book list, approximately 1950-1959; 1 pages (Box 19, Folder 11)
    List of book titles and call numbers of books by Frank R. Leavis, in Plath's hand. List is on the back of a library catalogue card.
  - Memorabilia: Ceramic tile and pendant from Seventeen Magazine, approximately 1950-1959 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Ceramic tile and pendant in the form of the numeral '17'. Paper attached to the tile has the printed message, "Holiday Greetings from all of us at Seventeen."
  - Memorabilia: Shopping list (Box 19, Folder 13)
    Handwritten shopping list on the back of a Smith College Official Class card, 2nd semester 1957-58, for Emmy Thomas Pettway, for English 11.
    Found in Plath's copy of T.S. Eliot, by Elizabeth Drew (Mortimer Rare Book Collection, 825 P696L Dr.).
  - Memorabilia: Rose petal (Box 19, Folder 14)
    Found in Plath's copy of Cleanth Brooks' Understanding Poetry pages 554-55 (Mortimer Rare Book Collection, 825 P696L Br).
  - Memorabilia: Photocopies of sheet music, approximately 1956; 11 Leaves (11 leaves; 42 cm.) (Box 19, Folder 14.1)
    Photocopies of covers of piano sheet music owned by Sylvia Plath. Four leaves have her signature; three have notes by Aurelia Plath.
    Original sheet music in Newnham College, Cambridge Archives.
    Custodial History
    Sheet music was left by Plath in her rooms at Newnham College, circa 1956.
    Gift of Ben Stuit, 8/9/1999.
  - Memorabilia: Maps of Paris, Nice, and France., approximately 1950 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    Maps of Paris, Nice, and France with the name of a hotel and room number written by Plath inside the front cover. Also with handwritten note by Aurelia Plath.
  - Memorabilia: Front cover of Audience: A Quarterly Review of Literature and the Arts, autumn 1958 (Box 19, Folder 15.1)
  - Memorabilia: Dust jacket to Light Blue Dark Blue: An Anthology of Oxford & Cambridge Writing, approximately 1960 (Box 19, Folder 15.2)
    Dust jacket only. The list of writers includes Ted Hughes. Ted Hughes' "Macaw and Little Miss" was published in the 1960 edition of Light Blue Dark Blue.
  - Memorabilia: Typescript of "A brief biography", approximately 1960; 1 pages (Box 19, Folder 16)
    Typescript lists Sylvia Plath's birth date, degrees, awards, and jobs through 1959. "Palatino," possibly instructions to a printer, is written at the bottom.
  - Memorabilia: Notes from Ted Hughes to Sylvia Plath (Box 19, Folder 17)
    Two handwritten notes from Ted to Sylvia and one riddle from Sylvia to Ted in an envelope with typing, "Handwritten verses from Ted to Sylvia that accompanied gifts and special occasions."
    Gift of Aurelia S. Plath.
  - Memorabilia: Signed bookmark, undated (Box 19, Folder 18)
    Signed bookmark inscribed, "Love - Sylvia & Ted." "Ted" is in Ted Hughes' hand.
  - Notes concerning French vocabulary, 2 pages; Written on pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 19, Folder 19)
    Handwritten lists of French/English vocabulary, and a short list of works by Jean-Paul Sartre.
  - Note in German, approximately 1958; 2 pages (Box 19, Folder 20)
    One page typed (carbon), in German, titled Zwolftausend, with handwritten signature and annotations in ink by Plath (in English and German). One page handwritten notes by Plath, in English, with German study schedule.
    Found in Plath's copy of: Roseler, Robert Oswald. German in review. New York, 1953 (MRBC 825 P696L Ros).
  - Notes concerning German vocabulary, 4 pages; Written on pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 19, Folder 21)
    Handwritten notes of German/English vocabulary and passages in German.
  - Notes concerning Ibsen, 2 pages (Box 19, Folder 22)
    Miscellaneous list of titles and library call numbers of books by and about Ibsen.
    Found (laid in front) in Plath's copy of: Sophocles. The Theban Plays [Harmondsworth, Middlesex, 1956] (MRBC 825 P296L Sot).
  - Notes concerning Jung, 1959; 1962; 4 pages (Box 19, Folder 23)
    Handwritten notes, headed: JUNG. One-half page of translations from St. John Perse. Notes include items on the development of personality and on marriage.
  - Notes concerning Marvin Kane, 1 pages (Box 19, Folder 24)
    Handwritten notes by Plath possibly from an interview (?) with Marvin Kane. Page headed: Marvin Kane 9 Holland Park London W. 11 Park 6928.
  - Herman Melville quotations, 1 Leaves 5 x 7 inches; On pink Smith College memorandum paper. (Box 19, Folder 25)
    Two handwritten quotations, with page references, from Melville's Moby Dick.
    Found in Plath's copy of Melville's Moby Dick (MRBC 825 P696L Mel).
  - Memorandum notebook, probably 1944; 42 pages 3 ½ x 6 (Box 19, Folder 26)
    Includes outline of a book about "Nancy," poems and phrases, and a story titled "The thrilling journies of a penny." Written in memorandum notebook. "Sylvia Plath, 1944" written on cover. "O.E. Plath" embossed on cover. Handwritten note by Aurelia Plath: "(Jr. High School age) Plan for a book."
  - Notes concerning William Stafford, maybe 1961 (Box 19, Folder 28)
    Handwritten notes by Plath possibly for a review of poems (?) by William Stafford. Written on an envelope (postmark: 1961 Mar 21).
  - Untitled notes, undated; 2 items (Box 19, Folder 29)
    Stream-of-consciousness description: typescript and handwritten sentence, in quotations, about rain and fog.
  - Scrapbook and photocopies of separated pages (Box 45)
    Sylvia Plath created an album of clippings of three dozen of her poems, four articles, one letter, and one review of her poem "Spinster" in a commercial album. This box contains the original album with blank pages and photocopies of the separated materials. Photocopies note their original page number in the album. Some pages of the album have handwritten captions remaining.
    All of the original clippings were removed from the album.
    Originals are filed in the poems, prose, reviews, and correspondence series.
- School papers, approximately 1945-2000; 1949-2007; 4; .5 linear feet (1 box)
  This series contains papers written, and sometimes illustrated, by Plath in Junior and Senior High School, as well as items from Smith College and Cambridge University.
  - Phillips Junior High School: "Plans of Union" holograph, 1945 March 20; 8 pages (8 pages (some blank), laid in cover; illustrated.) (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Phillips Junior High School: "George Washington" holograph, 1945 March 27; 12 pages (12 pages (some blank); illustrated.) (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Phillips Junior High School: "A war to end wars" holograph, 1946 February 26; 46 pages (46 pages (some blank) laid in cover; illustrated) (Box 20, Folder 3)
    Original is fragile, please use provided photocopy.
  - Phillips Junior High School: "Evangeline" holograph, 1946 May; 14 pages (14 pages laid in cover); Cover is illustrated with an ink and watercolor drawing of Evangeline. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Phillips Junior High School: "The world and the United States" holograph, 1946; 86 pages (86 pages (some blank) laid in cover; illustrated) (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Phillips Junior High School commendation card, 1947 June 13 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    Commendation card "...to Sylvia Plath for punctuality for three years at Junior High School." Card is signed by teacher and principal.
  - Bradford Senior High School: The Bradford, 1949 June 7 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    The Bradford volume 5, number 6. Plath is among incoming editors announced in an article and photograph on page 1.
  - Bradford Senior High School: Program for graduation exercises, 1950 June 7 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    Program for grauduation exercises at Gamaliel Bradford Senior High School with two admission tickets.
  - Bradford Senior High School: The Wellesleyan: The Year Book of the Gamaliel Bradford Senior High School, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    Gift of Richard W. Vauer, 3/17/2000.
  - Bradford Senior High School: Wellesley High School Class of 1950 50th Reunion Book, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    Class of 1950 reunion book with a photocopy of the Wellesley High School Class Song (1950) with lyrics by Sylvia Plath.
    Gift of James E. Gately, 6/14/2001.
  - Smith College: Letter from Ruth W. Crawford to Aurelia Plath, 1949 October 1 (Box 20, Folder 11, Item 1)
    Typed and signed letter from Ruth W. Crawford, Director of Admission, to Aurelia Plath, thanking her for her interest in Smith College and enclosing an application card. With envelope and annotation in shorthand by Aurelia Plath.
  - Smith College: Copy of letter from Ruth W. Crawford to Aurelia Plath, 1949 October 5 (Box 20, Folder 11, Item 2)
    Copy of a typed letter from Ruth W. Crawford to Aurelia Plath, thanking her for sending her daughter's registration fee and placing Sylvia on the list of applicants for admission to college. With two typed pages headed "To Candidates for Admission in 1950." Handwritten annotations are by Aurelia Plath.
  - Smith College: List of books read and high school activities, probably 1950 (Box 20, Folder 11, Item 3)
    Typewritten list of books read and high school activities, used for application to Smith College (according to Aurelia Plath, who typed the list and added comments). Handwritten note by Aurelia Plath.
  - Smith College: Letter from Ruth W. Crawford to Sylvia Plath, 1950 May 10 (Box 20, Folder 11, Item 4)
    Typed and signed letter from Ruth W. Crawford to Sylvia Plath announcing her acceptance to Smith College.
  - Smith College: Note from the Office of the Warden, undated (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 1)
    Note concerning housing costs and preferences.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath, 1949 November 15 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 2)
    Typed and signed letter form Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath enclosing general information about scholarships and cooperative houses.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath, 1949 November 21 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 3)
    Typed and signed letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath indicating that they have received her preliminary application for scholarship aid.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to all scholarship applicants, 1950 January 3 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 4)
    Typed letter Mary E. Mensel to all scholarship applicants regarding application process, with handwritten annotation by Aurelia Plath.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to all scholarship applicants, undated (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 5)
    Typed letter (carbon) from Mary E. Mensel to all scholarship applicants regarding the application process with handwritten annotation by Aurelia Plath about Sylvia's interests and hobbies.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath, 1950 January 4 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 6)
    Typed and signed letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath referring her to the scholarship representative of the Wellesley Smith Club.
  - Smith College: Letter from Elizabeth Cannon Aldrich to Mary E. Mensel, 1950 February 3 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 7)
    Typed letter, possibly carbon, signed from Elizabeth Cannon Aldrich recommending Sylvia Plath for scholarship assistance.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath, 1950 May 10 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 8)
    Typed and signed letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath informing her that she has not been assigned to a cooperative house.
  - Smith College: Mary C. Ford and Aurelia Plath correspondence, 1951 May 10; 1951 May 13 (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 9)
    Autograph letter (signed) from Mary C. Ford to Aurelia Plath announcing $400 scholarship from Wellesley Smith Club for 1951-1952. Also included are envelope, and typed draft of Aurelia's response dated 1951 May 13 as well as a handwritten note by Aurelia about Sylvia Plath's scholarship grants.
  - Smith College: Letter from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia Plath, 1952 June 23; 1 pages (1 page with envelope) (Box 20, Folder 12, Item 10)
    Typed letter (signed) from Mary E. Mensel to Sylvia plath announcing $900 scholarship for 1952-1953.
  - Smith College: Receipt for $50 deposit, probably 1950 May 20 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Smith College: Gymnasium outfit postcard, 1950 June 19 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    Card from Wright & Ditson acknowledging order for gymnasium outfit.
  - Smith College: Riding permission slip, approximately 1950 (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Smith College: Letter from K. Frances Scott to Sylvia Plath, 1950 June 28 (Box 20, Folder 16, Item 1)
    Typed letter from K. Frances Scott to Sylvia Plath indicating that she must take an exam to be exempt from the hygiene requirement at Smith.
  - Smith College: Postcard from K. Frances Scott to Sylvia Plath, 1950 July 6 (Box 20, Folder 16, Item 2)
    Typed postcard from K. Frances Scott to Sylvia Plath informing her that her name has been placed on the list to take the hygiene exemption examination, with annotation by Aurelia Plath indicating that Sylvia took the exam and was exempted.
  - Smith College: Who's Who in 1954, fall 1950 (Box 20, Folder 16.1)
    Who's Who in 1954, Smith College, fall 1950, with typed letter (signed) from Mary McBreen (Smith College class of 1952) asking for submissions for the "Who's Who…." Freshman class welcome booklet. The cover has the signature of Enid Lois Epstein and book is annotated by her. Entry, with photograph, of Plath on p. 36.
    Gift of Enid Epstein Mark, 1/18/2001.
  - Smith College: Notes for English 211: 20th Century, probably spring 1952; 12 pages 12 pages (last blank) (Box 20, Folder 17)
    Holograph notes for Notes for English 211: 20th century, Miss Drew (Fall term of English 211: 19th century).
  - Smith College: Letter from Benjamin F. Wright to Aurelia Plath, 1951 May 7 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    Typed letter from Benjamin F. Wright, president of Smith College, to Aurelia Plath announcing a raise in tuition for 1951-1952 with envelope, postmarked 1951 May 7.
  - Smith College: Borrower's cards Neilson Library books, 1951 May 19 - 1953 May 28; 9 items 9 items (one photocopy) (Box 20, Folder 18.1)
    Borrower's cards removed from Neilson Library books, with "S. Plath '54" written as one of many borrowers. Due dates May 19, 1951, April 2, 1953, and May 28, 1953. Cards for books by Elizabeth Bowen and by and about Edith Sitwell.
    Removed from books in Neilson Library stacks.
  - Smith College: The Smith College Associated News, 1952 March 11 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    Article from The Smith College Associated News about Plath as one of three candidates for Honor Board secretary, pages 3 and 4.
  - Smith College: Smith Weekly Current, 1952 April 17 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    Smith Weekly Current volume 5, number 15, containing an article about Plath taking over as Honor Board Secretary, p. 5, and clipping of similar news from "Neighborhood News," in The Townsman (Wellesley, MA), 1952 May 1, page 20, stapled to page 5.
  - Smith College: This is Smith College, 1953 May (Box 20, Folder 21)
    This is Smith College volume 4, number 1, article "Student self-government and responsible citizenship" by Enid Epstein, 54 (Smith College class of 1954). Article has handwritten annotations by Sylvia Plath and a photograph of her, as member of the Electoral Board, on page 2.
  - Smith College: Notes for English 321b: American literature, probably 1954; 12 pages 12 pages (last blank) (Box 20, Folder 22)
    Holograph notes for Notes for English 321b: American literature, Mr. Arvin.
  - Smith College: "A Check-list of the Published Writings of Gertrude Stein", 1954; 8 pages (8 pages and half sheet of errata) (Box 20, Folder 22.1)
    "A Check-list of the Published Writings of Gertrude Stein" compiled by George James Firmage, Amherst: University of Massachusetts, 1954. "Sylvia Plath" is inscribed on front cover in her own hand. With half sheet of errata inserted.
  - Smith College: Translation of Rainer Maria Rilke, "A Prophet.", probably 1954-1955; 2 pages (Box 20, Folder 22.2)
    Typescript of Sylvia Plath's translation of Rainer Maria Rilke's "A Prophet" for German 12. One page is signed by Sylvia Plath with her handwritten changes. Includes a "literal" and "verse" translation. The second page is headed "Sylvia Plath German 12" and includes the completed translation.
  - Smith College: "Revisions" and "Alterations", approximately 1955; 2 pages (Box 20, Folder 22.3)
    Typescript of selected stanzas from poems by Sylvia Plath typed into two columns headed "Revisions" and "Alterations." One column is the original text, and the second is revision after comments by Alfred Young Fisher. Some underlining and a few comments (by Fisher) on "Revisions" page. May have been done for a Special Studies with Fisher.
  - Smith College: Smith College commencement program, 1955 June 6 (Box 20, Folder 23)
    Commencement program with "Adlai Stevenson" (speaker) written by Aurelia Plath on the cover.
  - Smith College: Smith College diploma, 1955 June 6 (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - Smith College: Photocopies of Smith College transcript, 1955; 3 pages (Box 20, Folder 25)
    Transcript of Sylvia Plath's courses and professors.
    Originals in Smith College Archives.
  - Cambridge University: Heffer's Plan of Cambridge, 1955 (Box 20, Folder 26)
    Heffer's Plan of Cambridge 5th edition (Cambridge: W. Heffer & Sons Ltd., 1955). Inscribed by Sylvia Plath: on the front cover ("Sylvia Plath Newnham"); on the back cover ("9/15 Sat. 25 Feb Fenners Dr. Davy"); and on the map (in section A6: "Whitestead *", and in A7: "*")
  - Cambridge University: Menu for college feast, 1956 October 11 (Box 20, Folder 27)
    Printed menu with handwritten annotations by Plath.
  - Cambridge University: Photograph of Newnham College (Box 20, Folder 28)
    Mounted photograph of Newnham College, Cambridge, England by A. Puck.
  - Cambridge University: Memories of Whitstead, 2007 January (Box 20, Folder 29)
    Memories and photographs of students at Whitstead, including Sylvia Plath.
    Gift of Rhoda M. Dorsey, 08-01-2007.
- Artwork, 1940-1960; 5; 2.5 linear feet (1 box; 2 oversize folders)
  Paintings, drawings, and collage made by Sylvia Plath. Plath often made drawings in her journals and her correspondence, as well as creating drawings and paintings, and both 'formal' and 'informal' creations are represented here. Originals of drawings and paintings are followed by photocopies of art that appears on items elsewhere in the collection. The location of the original is noted on the folder containing the photocopy.
  - "Chickens", 1940 April; 1 Leaves crayon and graphite 15 x 23 cm (Box 21, Folder 1)
    "Sylvia--April 1940 (age 7 1/2)" written in Aurelia Plath's hand on the reverse.
    Gift of Alice B. Tabor, in memory of Sylvia Plath, 03/06/1996.
  - Untitled collage, probably 1960 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    Collage includes images of Dwight D. Eisenhower, Richard Nixon, bomber, satellite, woman in bathing suit, text, etc.
  - Drawing of a girl's head, approximately 1940's; 1 items Watercolor 45 x 30 cm (folded to 22.5 x 30 cm) (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Purchased from Glenn Horowitz (McConnell-Bohning Fund) 02/01/2001.
  - Drawing of three heads, approximately 1940's; 1 items (30.5 x 30.5 cm) (Box 21, Folder 4)
    Watercolor drawing of three heads. The bottom edge is rough as if torn from larger sheet.
  - Drawing of man's profile, approximately 1940's; 1 items 21.5 x 14 cm (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Pen and ink drawing of a man's profile. Paper has rough edge as if torn from a larger sheet of newsprint.
  - Drawing of camel rider in desert, approximately 1941-1944; 1 items 35.5 x 28 cm (Box 21, Folder 6)
    Colored pencil drawing of a camel rider in the desert.
  - Drawing of fairy blowing horn, approximately 1941-1944; 1 items 15 x 11.5 cm (Box 21, Folder 7)
    Colored pencil and crayon drawing of fairy blowing a horn and labeled "Sylvia Plath" on the back by Aurelia Plath.
  - Drawing of two women and boys, probably 1944 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    Pencil drawing of two women pointing to a boy who is beating another boy with a baseball bat. Quotation at bottom: "Oh, Junior has always been a poor loser."
  - Drawings of the heads of two children, probably 1951; 2 items (3 drawings) (Box 21, Folder 9)
    Pencil drawings of the heads of two children. One is labeled "Susy". On the back of the drawing of the boy is a drawing of the same girl ("Susy") sitting in a chair.
  - Photocopy of a drawing of Ted Hughes, probably 1956 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    Photocopy of a drawing of Ted Hughes, Mortimer Rare Book Collection does not own the original drawing.
  - Clippings from The Christian Science Monitor of Sylvia Plath drawings, 2 items (Box 21, Folder 11)
    Clippings from drawings published in the The Christian Science Monitor along with a photocopy of the article containing the illustrations. The smaller drawing is from Plath's album, labeled "Cape Cod: Summer 1957."
  - Drawing of a woman's head and torso, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
    Pen and ink drawing of a woman's head and torso (clothed).
    Found in Plath's copy of Henry James' Selected Short Stories, p. 165, "The Pupil." (MRBC P696L Jahs)
  - "The Village Store", undated (Box 21, Folder 13)
    Pencil drawing title "The village store."
  - "The Docks, Portland, Maine", undated (Box 21, Folder 14)
    Pencil drawing title "The Docks, Portland, Maine."
  - Drawing of girl "angel" with guitar, undated (Box 21, Folder 15)
    Colored pencil drawing of girl "angel" with guitar.
  - Photocopies of three drawings, undated; 3 items (Box 21, Folder 16)
    Photocopies of three drawings, stove, shack and vegitation. The Mortimer Rare Book Collection does not own original drawings.
  - Floral multi-color woodcuts on greeting cards, undated; 5 items (Box 21, Folder 17)
    Initialed SP on print and on the back of the cards.
  - Painting of dancing couple, approximately 1945-1947; 1 items 27.5 x 21.5 cm (Box 21, Folder 18)
    Tempera painting of dancing couple.